Guide to the Phillip Shapiro Papers, ca. 1960-1985
Department of Special Collections
Shapiro, Phillip. Papers,
ca. 1960-1985
M0928
Shapiro, Phillip.
15.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Approximately a third of this collection consists of the papers from these two groups: publicity, minutes, organizational records, correspondence, and more. A second significant segment of these papers concerns Shapiro's involvements in the 1960s and 1970s, particularly those in support of the Black Panther Party for Self-Defense, and his work around prison issues, particularly the San Quentin Six. He also did work on medical aid for Vietnam, involvement in the Mobilization to End the War in Vietnam, and the rebuilding of Bach Mai hospital.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1997.
Biography
We've been told since out first childhood disappointment that life isn't fair. Dr. Philip Shapiro, a prominent Bay Area Psychiatrist and Human Rights activist for over a quarter of a century, lived his life as if to say "not if I have anything to do with it." Through his involvement with groups such as the Medial Committee for Human Rights, Physicians for Social Responsibility, the California Commission for the Protection of Human Subjects, and the Black Panther Party (among others) Dr. Shapiro fought for the common man, and for those who could not fight themselves. Beginning in the Late 60's with the MCHR's outspoken protests of America's involvement in Vietnam, it was apparent that Dr. Shapiro was a man who acted on what he believed. On top of his daytime employment as a respected psychiatrist at San Francisco's Mt. Zion hospital, Dr. Shapiro was a tireless worker who organized meetings, speeches, protest marches, and charity functions to raise public awareness of what he felt was an extremely inhumane course of action be taken by our Government. Through his connections in the MCHR, Dr. Shapiro was attracted to other causes which he felt could use his assistance- everything from subsidized hospitals in the ghettos of Oakland (in collaboration with the Black Panther Party) to anti-nuclear proliferation to the rights of those in prison. He struggled to ensure that every man, regardless of race, financial status or beliefs, was treated as a man. Dr. Shapiro passed away in 1995, leaving behind him lifetime of accomplishments, friends, and admirers.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The prominent San Francisco psychiatrist Phillip Shapiro stood at the forefront of the San Francisco Bay Area's progressive health workers for more than a quarter of a century, from the civil rights movement through the cold war of the 1980s. Dr. Shapiro's activities, particularly in issues relating to the medical profession, helped galvanize health workers into a politically active force. His archive consists of thirty-one boxes of written and printed materials and audiotapes, some fifteen linear feet in all. Dr. Shapiro became the West Coast mainstay of the medical Committee for Human Rights (MCHR) which worked on human rights issues related to the practice of medicine. He also worked with Physicians for Social Responsibility (PSR), the Nobel Prize-winning group that opposed the building and proliferation of nuclear weapons. Approximately a third of the collection consists of papers from these two groups, including publicity, minutes, organizational records, and correspondence. A second significant segment of the papers includes Dr. Shapiro's activities in the 1960s and 1970s, particularly those in support of the Black Panther Party and work on prison issues and the San Quentin Six. The collection also contains papers relating to medical aid for Vietnam as well as his involvement with the Mobilization to End the War in Vietnam and the rebuilding of Bach Mai hospital. Dr. Shapiro's work with the prison support movement led to his involvement in groups opposing medical procedures on unwilling prisoners and unsuspecting patients in the larger medical care system. The latter part of the collection concerns the issue of prisons and Psychosurgery, as well as his involvement with the Committee for the protection of Human Subjects. Other materials include tape recordings of radio shows, news conferences, conferences and other public events relevant to his interests, as well as files relating to his professional interests. Finally, it is important to note that Dr. Shapiro made copies of his own correspondence; from these it will be relatively easy for researchers to identify the context of much of the material found in the collection.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Cleaver, Eldridge.; Cleaver, Kathleen.; Hilliard, David.; Huggins, Erika.; Newton, Huey P.; Pratt, Geronimo.; Seale, Bobby.; Bach Mai Hospital.; Black Panther Party for Self-Defense.; Committee for Protection of Human Subjects.; Medical Committee for Human Rights (MCHR); Mobilization to End the War in Vietnam.; Physicians for Social Responsibility (PSR); The San Quentin Six.; Medicine.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Vietnam Protests
  - Vietnam War Protests (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Protest Clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - SF Protest Clippings (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - SF Protest Fliers (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - SF GI March for Peace (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Vietnam GI (Newsletter) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Proposition "P" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Spring Mobilization Committee (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Spring Mobilization Financial Documents (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Spring Mobilization Minutes/Letters (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Spring Mobilization Cultural and Labor Issues (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Spring Mobilization & Prof. comm.. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Spring Mobilization Steering Committee (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Spring Mobilization- Miscellaneous Documents (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Friends Served Committee (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bay Area Poor People's Campaign (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Health Professionals for Peace (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Medical Aid for Indochina, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Medical Aid for Indochina (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Medical Aid for Indochina (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Committee Against Repressive Legislation (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Support our Soldiers (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Veterans for peace (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Peace Organizations (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Peace Organizations (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Peace Organizations (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Berkley Student Protest (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bombing of Dykes (Political Correspondence) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Civil Rights (Political Correspondence) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sons & Daughters (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Peace Torch Marathon (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Port Chicago Vigil (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Red Star Singers, Vancouver Peace Conference (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Vietnam Pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hanoi Prisoners' Short Wave Broadcast (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - In Search (Newsletter) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Cold War Articles (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Vietnam War Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Vietnam War Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The History of the World (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series 2. The Black Panther Party
  - Black Panther Party National Documents/ Releases (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fliers (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Articles (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bail-Bond Fund (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Elaine (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cleaver, Eldridge and Kathleen (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Cleaver, Eldridge and Kathleen (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Cleaver, Eldridge and Kathleen (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Davis, Angela (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Genet, Jean (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Hilliard, David (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Huggins, Erika (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Hutton, Bobby (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newton, Huey (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Free Huey Newton (Peace and Freedom Party) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pinell, Hugo (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Pratt, Elmore and Geronimo (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Seale, Bobby (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Valvedere, Jose (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Party Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Educational Opportunities Corporation (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Panther Relations with MCHR (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series 3. Physicians for Social Responsibility
  - PSR 1962-67 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - PSR 1978-82 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - PSR 1978-82 II (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Old Newsletters (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Steering Committee 1979-82 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Steering Committee 1983-84 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Steering Committee 1984 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising Affairs (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Position Papers (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer's Report (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Speakers File (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Rosters (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Committee Reports (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Memos (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - PSR/West (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - SF Chapter (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bay Area Chapter By-laws (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - PSR Reports (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Clippings (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Clippings II (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Early Clippings (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Civilian Military Contingency Hospital System (CMCHS) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - CMCHS Editorial Rebuttal (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - CMCHS PSR Official Statement (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - CMCHS PSR letters to hospitals (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - CMCHS American Public Health Association resolution (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - CMCHS Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - CMCHS Clippings (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - PSR Alert! (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Arms Control (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Arms Control Clippings (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Civil Defense (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Civil Defense Clippings (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Civil Defense Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Children & The Bomb (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The Defense Monitor (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Hiroshima Survivors (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Nuclear Test Ban (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - USS Missouri in SF (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - USS Missouri in SF (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Star Wars (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Facing the Music (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - SF Chapter Retreat (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Nuclear Threat to SF (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Nuclear Threat to SF (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - FEMA (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - FEMA of Oakland (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - World Peace Council (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - ESR - Educators for Social Responsibility (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Professionals Coalition for Nuclear Arms Control (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - IPPNW - Int'l. Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Ali, Joan (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Allen, Dave (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Heffernan, Pat (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Kornfield, Howard (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Lown, Bernard (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Moxley III, John (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - O-Flaherty, Terrence (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Peck, Harris (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Quin, John R (Archbishop) (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Sapir, Marc (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Thomas, Lewis (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Torres, Hiram (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Trainor, Dorothy (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Congressional Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Briefing Papers (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - EAS Public Interest Report (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - IPPNW Sticker (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - PSR- Miscellaneous Documents (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - PSR- Miscellaneous Publications (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - PSR- Miscellaneous Publications (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Series 4. Medical Committee for Human Rights
  - MCHR National Documents (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - National Convention (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - National Newsletters (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - National Health Taskforce (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Government Relations (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - MCHR-SF (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Steering committee -- Bay Area Chapter (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Other Committees and Meeting Notes- SF (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters (Local) (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Chicago Chapter (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - MCHR Clippings (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - American Medical Association (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - California Medical Association (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - EPDST-Summaries of Programs (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - EPDST-Articles and Clippings (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - EPDST-Legislation and Health Care Connections (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - EPDST-NY Department of Social Services Report (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - EPDST-Related Correspondence (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Child Trauma Intervention Act (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - False Drug Advertising (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Health Care Reform (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Committee for Howard Levy (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Mace as a Riot Control Agent (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Occupational Health Project (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Prison issues (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Medical Logo Stencils (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - CPHS-Policy Statement and Goals (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Personnel (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Administration I 1977-78 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Administration II 1978-80 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Agendas (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Decisions1977-78 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Decisions1979-81 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Legislation- Federal (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Legislation- Federal (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Legislation- State (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Memos (Health & Welfare Agency) (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Minutes1977-78 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Minutes1978-81 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Articles I (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Articles II (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Protocol guidelines, policy statements (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Protocols Deferred (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Protocols Pending (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Committees- Approved Protocols (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Committees- Approved Protocols (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Committees- Approved Protocols (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Thomas Dalglish (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Thomas Dalglish (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Thomas Dalglish (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Thomas Dalglish (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Charles Gardipee (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - IRB- "A Review of Human Subject Research" (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Notification of meetings (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Non-Agenda Items (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Presidio Mutiny Trial (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Series 5. Committee for the Protection of Human Subjects and other Organizations
  - BAEAC (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - BAI Newsletter (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - CCCO (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Health Professionals for Peace (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - HPFP- Fliers and Pamphlets (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - HPFP- Clippings (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - HPFP- Correspondence (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - HPFP- Miscellaneous (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - OSPAAL (Box 18, Folder 15)
- Series 6. Prison Issues
  - Administrative Segregation (Solitary Confinement) (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Violence in Prison- State Report (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Gang Violence in Penal Institutions (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Gay Prisoners (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Prison Legislation (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Evaluation of State Prison Medical Facility (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - SF Jails (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Police/Community Relations (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - California State Prison Documents (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Houston Neurological Symposium (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Prisoner Rights-Open Files (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Federal Prisons - Clippings (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - California Prisons - Clippings (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - San Quentin - Clippings (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - San Quentin Six - Clippings (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - San Quentin Six and Soledad (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - San Quentin Six and Soledad (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - SF Jails- Clippings (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - National Prison Clippings (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Prisoner Publications (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - ACLU (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Bay Area Prisoner Organizations (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Coordinating Council of Prison Organizations (CCPO) (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Community control of police (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Committee for Prisoner Humanity and Justice (CPHJ) (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Joint Action and Strategy Team (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Prison Action Conference (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Prisoners' Health Project (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Prison Law Project (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Prison Law Collective (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - California v. Gibson and Justice (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - California v. Gibson and Justice- First Appeal (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - California v. Gibson and Justice- Subsequent Appeals (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Gibson/Justice Defense Fund (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Davis, Julio (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Johnson, John D (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Justice, Lawrence (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Thorne, John (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Stender, Fay (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Prisoners as Experimental Subjects (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Public Advocates for Prison Rights (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - SF Prison Health Needs Conference (MCHR) (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Biomedical Experimentation in California Prisons (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - S.T.A.R.T. Program (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Hastings Center Report (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Hastings Center Reports (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Prisoners and Drugs (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Forced Medication to Prisoners (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Committee for Prisoner Health (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - United Prisoners Union (UPU) (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Vacaville Stress Assessment Unit (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Penal Code Symposium- UCSF (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Patients Rights and Advocacy- MCHR Pamphlet (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - national Commission on Psychosurgery (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Neuropsychiatric Experimentation on Prisoners (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Biomedical Experimentation on Prisoners (Box 23, Folder 11)
- Series 7. Psychosurgery
  - Psychosurgery Documents (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Psychosurgery: Legal Issues (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Psychosurgery: California State Supreme Court Case (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Kaimowitz v. Michigan Department of Health (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Network of Psychiatric Assault (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Committee Opposing Abuse of Psychiatry (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Committee Opposing Abuse of Psychiatry (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Drug Therapy and Psychosurgery Group Statements (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Genetic Causes of Violence (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - California Medical Facility at Vacaville (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - UCLA Center for the Study and Control of Violence (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - UCLA Center- Grant Application (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - UCLA Center- Group Statements (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - UCLA Center- State Department of Health Documents (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - UCLA Center- Protests (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - UCLA Center- Clippings (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - UCLA Center- Related Correspondence I (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - UCLA Center- Related Correspondence II (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Psychosurgery Clippings1971-72 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Psychosurgery Clippings1973 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Psychosurgery Clippings1973 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Psychosurgery Clippings1974 (and later) (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Psychosurgery-related Correspondence (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Prisoner Correspondence (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Prisons- Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Mt. Zion Hospital Psychiatric Clinic (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Mt. Zion Hospital Psychiatric Clinic (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Drug Abuse and Alcoholism Newsletter (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Drug Abuse and Alcoholism Newsletter (Box 27, Folder 8)
- Series 8. Correspondence
  - Ali, Joan (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Blackman, Vernon (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Blackman, Vernon (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Coleman, Lee (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Garry, Chris (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Political Correspondence (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Snyder, Marc (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Spieglman, Richard (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Spock, Dr. Benjamin (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Wilson, Pete (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - The Conspiracy Newspaper 1974-76 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Health Professionals for Peace (Box 29, Folder 3)
- Series 9. Audiovisual materials
  - Recordings, 7 sound reels: 5 in. + 4 audiocassettes (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Recordings, 18 audiocassettes (Box 31, Folder 1)